[music]
Okay, [music] good morning everybody.
Who was in the workshop yesterday? Let's
see how many people Hey. Okay, welcome
to code security reinvented. Navigating
the era of AI. I really want to build to
what we knew from yesterday. Let's see
how this looks like. So starting with a
statement AI in the ID can help
developers with security. It sounds like
a bold statement but I'll show you
different cases and I'm sure I can
convince you. The first case is writing
safer code. Let's start the other way
around. I want you to understand how not
to do so. How not to write safer code.
So on the code you see on the right just
to keep things flowing and smooth we
have I'm going to tell you what the
problem is. Uh line 23 SQL injection
let's try to detect that with AI.
So I'm running here the prompt list the
security issues in the code and propose
code to fix each of them. And we are
using GitHub copilot. It's a bit older
version for those who are familiar with
it. It doesn't matter. Okay, at the top
we see that SQL injection is indeed
recognized as a problem. That's
accurate. Yeah, but then you see
passwords in plain text. That's a
hallucination.
This is something that our code doesn't
suffer from. So hallucination is the
number one thing you are going to get
should you rely on AI to detect issues.
The number two I want to show you is the
following. I have the code from
yesterday imported on the left. You see
seasons one and two. Season 3 is not
important in this one. And I'm running a
very similar prompt with the hashtag
codebase in order to have my whole
codebase the 10 problems this codebase
is suffering from in the context of
copilot.
And when running that copilot came back
with eight problems. Somebody can say so
do we have 80% accuracy? I wouldn't say
so. But some of these issues, I've seen
them for the first time being reported
just just like prototype pollution in
number six. Prototype pollution occurs
when you have a parent method
injecting or maliciously giving
information to a child method. That
caught my eye and I said, "Huh, I'm a
security specialist and I'm seeing
prototype pollution detected by AI for
the first time." And you know let's open
the specific file that was there put it
in context here you have it code.js and
run the exact same prompt right and the
results do not have pollution inside. So
this shows you the second problem that
we suffer from which is nondeterminism
when it comes to detecting issues with
AI or relying on that.
However, I said, well, let's change the
model. Maybe open AAI didn't do as good
job as anthropic. Changing the model,
same stuff. Pollution didn't come up as
you are going to see now. And I'm
running my prompts uh for one time every
time. Uh some minor HDMI issues. So, as
you see, pollution is not there. Now,
what you had there was how can I fix
that? And this brings me to something
that I really want you to take away from
today. In cyber security, we don't have
a detection problem. We have a fixing
problem. Okay? So, we have so much tools
for all these years that give us so much
information about problems in our code,
false, positive, whatever. We just have
the info. Okay. But we don't have the
skills. We actually have one application
security specialist for every 100
developers. But with AI, we can fix
stuff as long as we are careful enough
and we read the code that AI suggests
and we make sure we don't introduce
other problems. Okay. So when it comes
to fixing the results are much higher
quality. There are filters to prevent
vulnerable stuff stuff from being
suggested. As long as you don't rely on
those and you read the code, you are in
a good shape. Now I want to show you the
same stuff but with agent mode enabled
because of the idea that with agentic AI
we have for example an AI agent that is
security specialized and then an AI
agent that is specialized in writing
JavaScript and in this specific case we
had the agent actually detecting the
pollution as you see here in number two
and at the same time the fixes we are
good but you shouldn't today 19 of
November 2025 rely on AI for detecting
issues. This is because while AI can
help minimize the security gap is not
here to replace security testing. The
security testing we use is built for
security testing because it has taint
tracking capabilities data flow
capabilities. While the AI we have is
predicting the next keyword either
English keyword or another language or a
coding keyword is not good at detecting
stuff. So as developers always follow
good security hygiene. AI shouldn't be
your only as you see with caps and only
is the keyword here safety net. MCPS to
the rescue. So I've seen the previous
sessions. I agree with the presenters. I
want to go a bit deeper though. Okay. So
for those that are not familiar, the MCP
is a standardized protocol so that the
agent the AI model can exit from the
training that was done and get access to
realtime data, get access to server side
information such as our accounts.
When we detect issues with AI, as we've
seen in practice, yes, we suffer from
nondeterminism. It may miss, it may
hallucinate. But at the same time, we
have a unique opportunity to model
things with natural language that we
don't have with tooling like such as
static application security testing for
example that on the contrary gives us
high confident results that are
deterministic.
And here I want you to notice what we
have at the top. What about the security
MCP server that combines both? Ideally,
we are working on that. And I'm in the
position to say that the user experience
is not nice. We have to improve on that
before we release anything like that as
GitHub. And I can go in more detail. The
MCP protocol is synchronous, right? So
for a static application security
testing tool for code scanning for
example, when we try to use it, the user
experience is slow, is really bad. And
then we try to put that in on the ID
level and then have an AI agent
commenting on the result or helping the
user with the result, orchestrating
different tooling. It's not nice. It's
not working. That's a goal, but it we
are not there yet. Okay, it's just
something ideal as developers. Now, when
it comes to these tools in action, for
me personally as security specialist,
it's hard to trust an MCP server that I
don't use already. For example, if I use
Figma, it makes sense to trust their
RMCP server because I already use them,
right? And why I don't trust them? First
of all, I've seen a lot of MCP servers
that are asking for overly broad scope
too much. my stuff in the ID is going to
get exposed on the outside then indirect
prom injections as you saw from
yesterday 100% possible yesterday in the
workshop you were typing the prompt
right imagine when I have a list of
prompts ready to attack you from the
inside that's the number two things top
two things I would say um then a lot of
MCP servers here and there the VS code
try to have its own registry GitHub came
up with its own registry as well. Have a
look at those. When it comes to
security, I've only seen two servers
there. The one from Kodasi, which is a
company um and the one of GitHub. The
one of GitHub is not specialized in
security, but there are some functions
you can use like for example this one
code security and the top two, the last
two, secret protection and security
advisories. The way you use them is that
you are in the agent mode and you use
one of those functions. So the MCP
server is going on the server side. You
should be authenticated and is taking
stuff that were server side as well. For
example, um the alerts that your code
has generated, the secrets that your
code has leaked. And what you get from
that is that you can have a chat about
it with your AI coding agent. At the
same time, you can save some time by
getting a security posture being
summarized for you, next steps, and so
on. Here the dis the disclaimer is that
you can get some stuff to get started,
but don't expect that copilot is like
the security expert, right? Is a coding
assistant. The information is good. Use
it to save some time. Use it to get
stuff on the ID level. It's really good
at that because the information is
structured is on the server is or in a
pull request is very
structured to the point that you
shouldn't expect hallucinations.
Now take better informed decisions when
it comes to your supply chain. This is
something that maybe it becomes an MCP
server in the future. It's something we
worked on in the past months and I'm
here to give it to you for free as all
the other stuff with you today. So you
can speed up your research for the
community health and security of a
package before this package becomes part
of your supply chain risk. Every time
you introduce something in your
codebase, you increase your attack
surface.
Let's be honest now. How many of you
spend more than 10 minutes, 15 minutes
to decide on a package you are going to
introduce in your code? Let's be honest,
right? Yeah. Okay. Nobody. Perfect. So
this one we tried to do it at the top
here. Tell me about the community health
and security of the Python package.
Well,
what you see is a struct
or X or be alerted for different
categories. So you have an executive
summary and then you can visit the URLs
that we looked for. And how we did that
we put together a set of instructions
that you can access in this URL is two
or three different files. You can modify
them to your liking. The two three
people that worked on that worked really
well to avoid hallucinations. I
extensively tested that. It's good. It's
working. Many people are asking me but
why it's more than one file? Because
this is how we achieved a quality that
makes me confident to show you this
publicly today with one file. We just
didn't do it. Maybe in the future. So
just copy those files, put them in your
uh ID level, ask those questions, make
better decisions when you introduce
stuff because later on you get problems
with your supply chain.
Next one, security guidance.
Um, we run a program internally called
secure opensource fund. We give $1.25
million which is 10,000 to 20 to 125
projects. And every single open source
project that we helped came with the
same question which was and you are
going to see it now on the web interface
of copilot. I'm in the web. I'm inside a
repo that I don't maintain such as
bootstrap. The question is, how can you
hack my project? What's my attack
surface? What are my problems? And these
125 projects are lucky because they get
us to have them answering that question.
They get the money, but what about all
the other people in this world that
don't have access to this specialist and
so on. So the number one question people
ask for projects they use or for
projects that they don't use such as
bootstrap that I don't maintain. it's a
project that I'm considering for example
in my supply chain is how can somebody
hack me with that as a security
specialist I will have to read millions
of lines or thousands of lines to come
up with a short list like this one such
as for example be careful when you use
the sidebars because they are might have
the option or the problem of cross-ite
scripting because you know they have
user input and so on. Having this short
list gives you the chance to again
decide about a code of somebody else.
Should you trust it? How you are going
to use it? And it's really good because
people are having this question.
Now a lot of developers find fuzzing as
something that they want to do because
you know code scanning they can't get
it. They can have their code being read.
But fuzzing is an outside inside
approach, right? When something is
public already. Imagine just a normal
email and password field. If you put
like a million inputs to that, maybe you
make it become slow. Maybe you make the
system to have undesirable behavior. If
you want to use an AI coding assistant
to generate something regarding fuzzing
for me, you get two different uh options
that are really strong. The first thing
is the fuzzing automation slashh
hardness.
For example, create a system for me that
is going to get inputs and is going to f
something that I want to fast. And as a
security specialist, this one, this
prompt here, can you generate the
fuzzing strings is where a lot of
security engagements get slow. They get
bottlenecked because the security
specialist have to come up with a lot of
inputs that have to be malformed or they
have to be very long or hacky stuff. And
for somebody that is not a security
specialist, this boilerplate code is
really useful. And you know what's
another thing that is really useful?
This blue text at the end that is
autogenerated.
It's designed to keep the conversation
going and it has helped me so many times
when I just didn't know what's next. Not
for security but for other developer
related stuff that I just don't have too
much experience. Then you can get
tailored answers. This is more on the
training side and is useful because here
we know that our code is suffering from
SQL injection. This is a very easy
injection so that everybody can
understand in line 23. But in reality in
the real world when it comes to cyber
security you can have dozens of ways
that a problem occurs.
There are dozens of variation of SQL
injection for example and as a developer
maybe you don't get to understand
recognize everything by default or
straight away. What you can do is that
you can get specific answers or
education or examples with coding on the
specific variant of the vulnerability
that your code suffers from. This is
also helpful to me because when I study
about vulnerab when I studied about
vulnerabilities everything was
theoretical and it doesn't mean that
because I understand in theory I can
recognize it in practice. So this is
something that connects the two worlds
theory and practice when it comes to dev
education.
One of the last topics of today is
fixing security issues. As we said in
the beginning in cyber security, we
don't have a detection problem, we have
a fixing problem. In the past,
let's go back. Uh when you find when you
have found a problem, you know about it
because maybe somebody hacked you or you
have penetration testers or you have
people reviewing code. The best practice
is to have code scanning in your CI/CD
of course. And the old experience before
AI was that you know you see the problem
that you get alerted for in your server
site for example whatever sonar cube
github you name it. Okay, then you see
the problem, you go back to your ID, you
fix that problem, you push the code
again and you see if the alert is there
or not. This is past
uh autofix which is free for open
source. You can test it in the code we
had yesterday that I'm going to provide
again in with autofix you fix this
problem straight away with AI on the ID
level within GitHub. We fixed 600
vulnerabilities in two weeks bringing
the fix rate from 50% to 100%. Our
client have reduced the time to
remediation which is important because
the more time they need to fix stuff,
they were fighting more internally. They
had competing priorities internally and
so on. So this is the old experience
that I told you about. You get in code
scanning, you see the alerts, you click
in the alerts, you read what they are
about, you go back to your code, you try
to fix that, you push again. No, the new
stuff looks like that. So this is a pull
request that I have pushed. I push the
feature, right? And the detection is
happening with a code scanning tool. We
are not relying on AI to detect. The
best practice is to use the expert tool
to detect. But we use AI to propose
fixes for that. So you get the
explanation here.
Come on.
Yeah, you get the explanation here
exactly where what the problem is, where
it occurs, what's the source of the
vulnerability, what's the scene of the
vulnerability, which means where it
really being executed.
Let me go back to that.
Uh
so I'm on the navigation again. Okay. So
basically what you are going to see here
is code uh in green color. That is the
usual code suggestions from GitHub being
suggested to you from AI on the PR
level. This code that is suggested to
you is guaranteed to remove the alert.
But you don't have to commit that code
if you don't want to. you can edit that
code inside the PR, not even in your ID
straight away without even opening code
spaces, but you can open if you want to
and then you can remove that alert. So,
in summary, today we covered six
different ways that today you can use AI
to ship more secure code. The number one
was to write safer code. Uh remember
always that you shouldn't rely on AI as
your only safety net. Don't use it to
detect stuff, use it to fix stuff.
Always read the code before that is
suggested to you. MCP to the rescue. We
saw that right now you can access
serverside stuff and use those with AI.
We are not where we dream to be with MCP
yet, but I hope we can get there. Supply
chain decisions. You can make better
decisions when you have a structured way
with AI to get the answers you want to.
If you don't want to rely on that, visit
the URL yourselves.
Uh, get tailor answers is all about
getting the guidance and education that
is tailored to the variant of the
vulnerability your code is suffering
from. Security guidance very similar to
the supply chain decisions. The
difference is that you are going to get
a short list of something you should be
careful of in case you use a code you
are not familiar with. Find and fix
security bugs. Copilot autofix is
something that is going to help you in
the same way that has helped us
internally and other open source project
becoming faster. Yesterday we played
what is in this repo here. gh.iose
io/secure
codegame abbreviated as SCG.
Use that repo as the playground to try
what I've shown you today for free. Have
your own experience before trying
anything in the code you own and you
care about. And for those that are not
in the workshop yesterday, this is a
repo with three different seasons. We
got amazing uh feedback from yesterday.
Was it fun? Yes, exactly. It was. So,
for those that didn't play, you can have
your own game there. And for those that
played, always remember that you have
season one and two as well. And you can
also be part of our community by
contributing following the
contribution.md.
That was me. Uh I love creating content
for developers and try to use a language
that is more developer friendly in cyber
security than what many other security
professionals are using. Trying to make
developers try to add value to
developers to understand the
vulnerability patterns and so on. You
may have seen me in the Instagram of
GitHub or Microsoft creating reals um
trying to raise awareness or in
different conferences such as this one.
Thank you so much. You've been a
fantastic audience. I'm here for your
questions and I'm also around in the
conference. Thank you so much.
[applause]
>> Thank you, Joseph. Uh, yeah, inspiring
as always. Thank you very much. Uh, we
might have time for one question if
somebody wants to ask a question. And
I'm sure you can find Joseph later if
you want to. So, no questions.
Everything's clear. That's good job.
Thank you. All right. [music]
Heat.
[music]
Heat. [music]